{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Despite being a puppet ruler, Chao Anouvong led a revolt in this modern-day country against one neighbor, though he was captured and imprisoned in Bangkok. This former vassal of Siam was occupied by a 14th-century kingdom whose name translates to \"one million elephants,\" the kingdom of Lan Xang. Champasak and Luang Prabang were two of three kingdoms that split this modern country, which was occupied by France and incorporated into their Indochina colony. For ten points name this neighbor of Vietnam that became Communist following a mid-twentieth century civil war.",
      "answer": [
        "Laos",
        "Lao People's Democratic Republic",
        "or Sathalanalat Paxathipatai Paxaxôn Lao"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Author Ken Kesey unknowingly took part in these experiments at the Veterans Administration Hospital in Menlo Park while working there as a night aide. One revelation from hearings on this project was that Frank Olson, a U.S. Army biochemist, died from being covertly dosed by an experimental drug under the auspices of this program. Originally designed to test the effects of psychoactive drugs on eliciting confessions during interrogations, for ten points, give the codename for what series of illegal and highly- secretive human experiments conducted by the CIA?",
      "answer": "Project MKUltra"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's grandfather with a similar name was pardoned by Martin van Buren after his violation of the Neutrality Act during the 1837 Upper Canada revolt. Heavy losses in the Dieppe Raid led to this leader instituting a national draft, leading to the Conscription Crisis of 1944. This longest serving prime minister of one country formally asked George VI permission to declare war on Nazi Germany. The leader of World War Two-era Canada was, for ten points, which Liberal prime minister?",
      "answer": "William Lyon MacKenzie King"
    },
    {
      "question": "Opponents of this man called the Erasistrateans resisted his theory that blood flowed through arteries, instead wrongly claiming pneuma did so. This man's records of treating the Antonine Plague while in Aquileia [[ah-KWIH-leh-uh]] led historians to identify the blight as smallpox. This man had his theories from On Anatomical Procedure untested for a millennium, until the 16th-century human dissections of Andreas Vesalius. For ten points, name this extremely influential Greco-Roman physician and scholar who expanded the Hippocratic views on humors.",
      "answer": [
        "Galen",
        "Aelius Galenus",
        "or Claudius Galenus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this war, General Abebe Aregai [[ah-REH-guy]] failed to stop the \"March of the Iron Will\" by the mechanized columns of Pietro Badoglio. The League of Nations was discredited following the proposal of the Hoare-Laval Pact, which agreed Britain and France wouldn't intervene in this war. Revanchist tendencies caused by the 1896 Battle of Adwa led to Mussolini organizing this war to created a unified \"Italian East Africa.\" The deposition of Haile Selassie occurred as a result of, for ten points, what war which led to an African nation's occupation?",
      "answer": "Second Italo-Ethiopian War"
    },
    {
      "question": "The killing of a sacred beast begins this nation's king-making ceremony, the Incwala, which coincides with the summer solstice. This nation's head of state was censured by Amnesty International after seizing 18-year-old schoolgirl Zena Mahlangu from her home. This nation's King Sobhuza II designed its flag, which depicts a black and white shield with multiple spears protruding from its side. For ten points, name this tiny kingdom between South Africa and Mozambique, ruled since 1986 by Mswati III.",
      "answer": "Kingdom of eSwatini or Kingdom of Swaziland"
    },
    {
      "question": "Merchant Harrison Gray Otis wrote Letters in Defense of [this meeting] while serving as overseer of Harvard University. Despite voting unanimously to not send a delegate to this meeting, a Vermont county sent one representative, William Hall Jr, anyway. A one-term presidential limit and prohibition of lengthy trade embargos were proposed at this convention populated exclusively by New England representatives. The Federalist Party collapsed following, for ten points, which purportedly treasonous \"Convention\" held in a Connecticut city?",
      "answer": "Hartford Convention"
    },
    {
      "question": "This Westerner reintroduced the works Alban Berg and Arnold Schoenberg, which had been repressed during the Socialist Realist period, while on a 1950s tour of the Soviet Union. While conducting Brahms Piano Concerto No. 1 in D minor for this man, Leonard Bernstein told the audience he assumed \"no responsibility for what they were about to hear.\" This soloist, who was known for eccentricities such as humming and foot-tapping while playing, began his recording career with a set of 30 contrapuntal variations Bach's Goldberg Variations. For ten points, name this Canadian pianist of the 20th century.",
      "answer": "Glenn Gould or Glenn Herbert Gould"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to Herodotus, a plan suggested by this client-king led to the death of Cyrus the Great while in battle with the Scythian Massagetae people. This king undertook the philosophical discussion known as \"Which man is Happy?\" with the Greek sage Solon, who suggested material wealth was too fickle to equate to happiness. This man's wife supposedly killed herself after the fall of his capital, Sardis. The first minting of metal coins is credited to, for ten points, which extremely wealthy, semi-mythological king of Lydia?",
      "answer": [
        "Croesus",
        "Krowiśaś",
        "or Kroisos"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This country secured its independence in the aftermath of Operation Storm, which included the retaking of Knin and the expulsion of many Orthodox Christians from Krajina [[krah-YEE-nah]]. During World War Two, a Nazi puppet state in this country was dominated by the Ustaše [[ooh-STAH-sheh]]. This country sought independence from Hungary and unification of its \"Triune Kingdom\" which included Slavonia and the coastal Kingdom of Dalmatia. For ten points, name this former Habsburg territory and constituent country of Yugoslavia, governed from Zagreb.",
      "answer": "Republic of Croatia or Republika Hrvatska"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country's second president, Robert Kocharyan, has been accused of plotting a 1999 shooting that killed its then-Prime Minister Vazgen Sargsyan. Kocharyan served as the leader of a neighboring unrecognized state, known as Artsakh, that this country took control of in a post-Soviet war against a neighbor whose capital is Baku. This country would lose much of Artsakh in a second war shortly after its 2018 Revolution to Azerbaijan. For ten points, name this Caucasian nation and ally of Nagorno-Karabakh.",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of Armenia",
          "Hayastani Hanrapetut'yun"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Armenia's 2018 revolution has been nicknamed for this type of cloth, which also names the 1989 Revolution in Czechoslovakia, alluding to the lack of violence in the course of the transition.",
        "answer": [
          "Velvet Revolution",
          "t'avshya",
          "sametová"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A vice-presidential candidate during this election year went on to serve as Ambassador of France during the Civil War. Andrew Jackson’s nephew was a vice- presidential candidate in this election year, during which Salmon Chase and William Seward withdrew their names from consideration. Anti-Catholic sentiment prompted the Know Nothing Party to run former-president Millard Fillmore in this election year, during which the first Republican National Convention was held. For ten points, in what election year did Republican John C. Fremont lose to Democrat James Buchanan?",
        "answer": "1856 United States Presidential Election"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "John C. Fremont would also lead this fringe political party, which was formed due to Abraham Lincoln's perceived moderate policies. This abolitionist party eventually withdrew from the 1864 election to avoid spoiling Lincoln's re-election.",
        "answer": [
          "Radical Democracy Party",
          "Radical Democrats"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Late 18th-century pianos often had a pedal named for either this place or a group from this place which simulated the sound of a bell or a bass drum. The makam system was used for music theory in this state, where genres included the fasil and pesrev. The tanbur lute and ney flute were often used in this state, where cymbal-heavy marching music was sometimes played by elite soldiers recruited from the Balkans. For ten points, Janissary bands originated in what empire, where music could be performed for the sultan in Constantinople?",
        "answer": [
          "Ottoman Empire",
          "Turkey",
          "or Turkish Empire",
          "Ottoman music",
          "or Turkish music"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What composer's eleventh piano sonata contains a final movement usually known as the \"Rondo Alla Turca\" for its Ottoman-inspired sound?",
        "answer": [
          "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart",
          "Johannes Chrysostomus Wolfgangus Theophilus Mozart"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This writer theorized that Marx failed to consider the crucial role of non-capitalist economies in sustaining the rate of profit in her 1913 economics treatise The Accumulation of Capital. Karl Vogel was likely the soldier who shot this woman and threw her body into the Landwehr Canal following chancellor Friedrich Ebert's authorization of the Freikorps to suppress her movement. For ten points, name this German Communist who was executed during the defeat of the Spartacist uprising in January 1919.",
        "answer": "Rosa Luxemburg"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Luxemburg and her frequent collaborator Karl Liebknecht [[LEEB-nekt]] were both members of this German political party, which they left for the Communist Party after this party openly supported the German war effort during World War One.",
        "answer": [
          "Social Democratic Party of Germany or Sozialdemokratische Partei Deutschlands",
          "SPD"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this scandal, women such as Madame de Montespan [[mohn-teh-SPAHN]] and Olympia Mancini were accused of using the euphemistically named \"inheritance powders.\" The informant Marie Bosse led police chief Nicholas de la Reynie to the person believed to be at the heart of this scandal, La Voisin [[vwah-SAHN]], or \"the neighbor.\" For ten points, name this scandal which culminated in 1682 and involved many French nobles being executed at the \"Burning Court\" for administering toxic substances to wealthy relatives.",
        "answer": "The Affair of the Poisons or L'affaire des poisons"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Almost exactly a century later, the French court was again scandalized by an affair named for this item, which was acquired by the Comtesse de la Motte using Marie Antoinette's forged signature.",
        "answer": [
          "Affair of the Diamond Necklace",
          "Affair of the Queen's Necklace",
          "or Affaire du collier de la reine",
          "or collier de diamants"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event led to the ten percent decrease in NASCAR race lengths and the cancellation of the 24 hours of Daytona in support of the government. Secretary of State Henry Kissinger's negotiating of the Israeli forces away from the Sinai peninsula led to the end of this crisis. The phrase \"Don't be Fuelish\" was used during this event, which was prompted by the Yom Kippur War. An embargo by the Organization of Arab Petroleum Exporting Countries during the Nixon and Ford administration led to, for ten points, which \"crisis\" of the late 20th century?",
        "answer": [
          "1973 Oil Crisis",
          "descriptions of the the US not having Oil in the 1970s",
          "OPEAC oil embargo of the 1970s"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The oil embargo was a direct response to which specific operation during the Yom Kippur War, in which the U.S. airlifted over twenty-thousand tons of military supplies to Israel?",
        "answer": "Operation Nickel Grass"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Several red-haired mummies discovered in this desert are believed to have spoken the extinct Indo-European Tocharian languages. The Gushi culture likely constructed the trading city of Gaochang in this desert. The nomadic Buddhist Dzungar [[ZOON-gahr]] people traveled along the Tarim Basin in this desert and conducted trade in cities such as Kashgar. For ten points, name this desert which was a significant trading center for the Uyghur [[WEE-gur]] peoples.",
        "answer": [
          "Taklamakan Desert",
          "Teklimakan Desert"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Territory in the Tarim Basin was briefly ruled during the time of Kanishka the Great by what Bactrian empire that used Greek in its administration, practiced Buddhism, and controlled much of present-day Afghanistan, Pakistan, and northern India?",
        "answer": "Kushan Empire"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author described his time living in Vermont in the memoir The Grain Between the Millstones. Another book by this man discusses events such as the Kengir Uprising and the process of segregating zeks. This frequent subject of the samizdat circulation process depicted the director Caesar and the Baptist Alyosha in a novel based on his own time as an Article 58 violator arrested by SMERSH. For ten points, name this Soviet author of The Gulag Archipelago and One Day in the Life of Ivan Denisovitch.",
        "answer": "Aleksandr Isayevich Solzhenitsyn"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A 1968 Solzhenitsyn novel is titled for a facility that treats this disease, which protagonist Oleg Kostoglotov analogizes to Stalinism.",
        "answer": [
          "Cancer",
          "Cancer Ward"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Women during the Civil War",
      "prompt": "Concerning women's many roles during the Civil War, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Conductor on the Underground Railroad who recruited black soldiers to fight for the Union cause.",
          "answer": "Harriet Tubman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Author of Little Women who depicted women during the Civil War in her non-fiction work, Hospital Sketches.",
          "answer": "Louisa May Alcott"
        },
        {
          "question": "Writer who Abraham Lincoln might have greeted by saying, \"you are the little woman who wrote the book that started this great war.\"",
          "answer": "Harriet Beecher Stowe"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of the American Red Cross who became known as the \"Angel of the Battlefield\" for her revolutionary nursing practices.",
          "answer": "Clara Barton"
        },
        {
          "question": "First woman physician in the U.S. who organized a corps of nurses during the Civil War.",
          "answer": "Elizabeth Blackwell"
        },
        {
          "question": "Private detective agency which employed the capable female P.I. Hattie Lawton to scout in the northern Virginia theater.",
          "answer": "Pinkerton Detective Agency"
        },
        {
          "question": "Boardinghouse owner and member of the Booth conspiracy to kill Lincoln who was the first woman executed by the federal government.",
          "answer": "Mary Surratt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hotel operator and Confederate spy known as \"the Siren of the Shenandoah.\"",
          "answer": "Isabelle Boyd"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ancient Troy",
      "prompt": "Concerning the legendary city of Troy, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern-day nation where the ruins of Troy were discovered.",
          "answer": "Republic of Turkey or Türkiye Cumhuriyeti"
        },
        {
          "question": "Blind poet who described Troy in the Iliad.",
          "answer": [
            "Homer",
            "Homeros"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Legendary King of Troy and father of Hector who names treasures smuggled out of it by westerners.",
          "answer": [
            "King Priam",
            "Priam's Treasure"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "or 1200s BCE.",
          "answer": [
            "Mycenaeans",
            "Mycenaean Greece"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Confederation of raiders whose invasion of New Kingdom Egypt may have been assisted by Western Anatolian people like the Trojans.",
          "answer": "Sea Peoples"
        },
        {
          "question": "Amateur German archeologist who discovered Troy in the 19th century.",
          "answer": "Heinrich Schliemann ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dead Anatolian language likely spoken by the inhabitants of Troy's sixth archaeological layer, and which is closely related to Hittite.",
          "answer": "Luwian"
        },
        {
          "question": "Greek ceramic containers whose decline in quantity indicated a regression of Troy's trade near the end of its seventh layer.",
          "answer": [
            "Pithoi",
            "Pithos"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "October Crisis",
      "prompt": "During the October Crisis, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Canadian province where French-speaking secessionism led to the October Crisis.",
          "answer": "Québec"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prime minister of Canada during the crisis who is the father of prime minister Justin.",
          "answer": "Pierre Trudeau or Pierre Yves Elliott Trudeau"
        },
        {
          "question": "City whose stock exchange and city hall were bombed during the crisis, as well as the home of its mayor Jean Drapeau.",
          "answer": "Montreal"
        },
        {
          "question": "French president who controversially promoted sectarian nationalism in Canada during his trip to Expo 67.",
          "answer": "Charles de Gaulle or Charles André Joseph Marie de Gaulle"
        },
        {
          "question": "Terrorist group whose bombings of public buildings started the October Crisis.",
          "answer": [
            "FLQ",
            "the Front de libération du Québec"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Phrase uttered by the prime minister when asked how far he would go to end the crisis.",
          "answer": "\"Just watch me.\" or \"Well, just watch me.\""
        },
        {
          "question": "Law invoked during the Crisis which suspended civil liberties.",
          "answer": "War Measures Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "Deputy premier kidnapped and murdered at the height of the crisis.",
          "answer": "Pierre Laporte"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A work about this entity uses Byzantine annals by George Hamartolus and John of Malalas. Histories of this polity are in the Radziwill Chronicle, including the Tale of Bygone Years. A monk from the Monastery of the Caves, Nestor, compiled this realm's history, which is in the (20 pts)",
        "Hypatian and Laurentian Codices. The Primary Chronicle of this political entity begins with the Severians fighting Viking brothers Sineus, Truvor and (10 pts)",
        "Rurik, the founder of Novgorod. For ten points, name this loose federation of Eastern European peoples, ruled by Vladimir the Great."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Kievan Rus' or Rusĭ",
        "Ruthenia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The principle at the center of this crisis was promoted by James Hamilton Jr. and William C. Preston, both representing the same state. The Force Bill was passed to allow the president to resolve this crisis with violence, though it was symbolically (20 pts)",
        "blocked by one side after a peaceful resolution was reached. A state ordinance declared the Tariffs of 1828 and 1832 unconstitutional, sparking this crisis, which was supported in the essay (10 pts)",
        "\"South Carolina Exposition and Protest\" by sitting-vice president John C. Calhoun. For ten points, name this constitutional crisis during the Andrew Jackson administration in which states attempted to block federal law."
      ],
      "answer": "Nullification Crisis"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Client-king Artabazos I of Phrygia [[frih-JEE-ah]] intentionally withheld his troops from participating in this battle, successfully retreating with his men to Ionia. The sole survivor of the \"300\" from (20 pts)",
        "Thermopylae, Aristodemus [[ah-ree-STOH- deh-mus]], was slain at this battle while attempting to redeem himself. According to legend, the Persian general Mardonius (10 pts)",
        "lost his life in this battle after a Spartan warrior smashed his skull with a rock. For ten points, name this final land battle during the second Persian invasion of Greece, which ended with a decisive Greek victory."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Plataea"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader personally led troops into Dai Viet after its Trần Dynasty was usurped by the popular general, Hồ Quý Ly [[HO KWEE LEE]]. This man overthrew his pacifist brother, the Jianwen Emperor, and ordered the construction of the (20 pts)",
        "Porcelain Tower and had the Grand Canal repaired. This emperor funded the \"Treasure Fleets\" of Muslim eunuch and Chinese admiral (10 pts)",
        "Zheng He [[ZHEHNG HUH]], who extorted tribute from various Indian Ocean states. For ten points, name this Ming Emperor who moved the imperial capital to Beijing."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Yongle Emperor",
        "Zhu Di"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Frauke Petry resigned from this party in favor of forming her own Blue Party, which dissolved following a 0.1 percent vote in Thuringia's general election. André Poggenburg was ousted from this party after publicly calling Turkish (20 pts)",
        "immigrants \"fatherless vermin.\" Björn Höcke [[HYOO-kuh]], a leader of this party, was accused of anti-Semitism after criticizing the existence of the Holocaust Memorial in (10 pts)",
        "Berlin as a \"Memorial of Shame.\" For ten points, name this populist right-wing party founded in 2013 in Lower Saxony."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Alternative for Germany",
        "Alternative für Deutschland",
        "or AdF"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This politician successfully tacked several progressive points to the Republican platform in the Election of 1960 by striking the \"Treaty of Fifth Avenue\" with Richard Nixon. This man died of a heart attack in the company of Megan Marshack, who mysteriously called a reporter before dialing 911, leading to theories of an affair. This politician ordered the National Guard to quash the (20 pts)",
        "Attica Prison Riot while serving as Governor of New York. This man later became vice president under another man who became president by rule of the (10 pts)",
        "Twenty-Fifth Amendment. For ten points, name this New York politician and vice president under Gerald Ford."
      ],
      "answer": "Nelson Aldrich Rockefeller"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Jewish people emigrating from this city to Cuba established 24 plants in the diamond-polishing industry during the Second World War. Hellburner ships, which have been described as early \"weapons of mass destruction,\" were used to stop an invasion of this city, taking place ten years after the most violent (20 pts)",
        "\"Spanish Fury.\" The fall of this city led to hundreds of Protestant merchants fleeing to the United Provinces across the border. This city's Bourse served as the world's first purpose- built commodity exchange. The trade hub of Bruges [[BROOJ]] was (10 pts)",
        "eclipsed in importance by, for ten points, which Flemish city?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Antwerp",
        "Antwerpen",
        "or Anvers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "Due to encouragement from Gloria Steinem, this figure ran in the Democratic primary for the Mayor of New York City using the slogan \"throw the rascals in.\" This author controversially compared American \"Hipsters\" to the African-American populace in the essay (*) \"The White Negro.\" This man's experiences as a cook in World War Two inspired his tale of a platoon of U.S. soldiers fighting on the fictional Anopopei [[ah-noh-POH-pay]] during the Pacific campaign. The Naked and the (*) Dead was written by, for ten points, which New Journalist and best-selling twentieth century American author?"
      ],
      "answer": "Norman Mailer or Norman Kingsley Mailer"
    }
  ]
}